<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
<channel>
                    <title>Social Sciences News - Psychology, Sociology</title>
            <link>https://phys.org/science-news/social-sciences</link>
            <language>en-us</language> 
            <description>The latest news on social sciences, history, political science, psychology and sociology</description>
                        <item>
                <title>Hidden patterns of isolation and segregation found in all American cities</title>
                <description>A comprehensive analysis of 383 U.S. cities reveals a striking pattern: most have rings of isolation in suburban areas and segregated pockets near the urban core, that are shaped by race, wealth, and proximity to downtown, finds a new study by UCL researchers.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-hidden-patterns-isolation-segregation-american.html</link>
                <category>Social Sciences Economics &amp; Business </category>
                <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 05:00:01 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684666048</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2024/isolation.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Popular song lyrics have become more negative since 1973, analysis reveals</title>
                <description>Over the past 50 years, the lyrics of popular songs in the U.S. have become simpler, more negative, and contain more stress-related words, according to an analysis published in Scientific Reports. The authors suggest that their findings reflect the complex ways people use music to navigate stress.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-popular-song-lyrics-negative-analysis.html</link>
                <category>Social Sciences </category>
                <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 11:00:07 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684583081</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/record-player.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Ear piercings marked one of the earliest Maya rites of passage, research shows</title>
                <description>In a recent study, Ph.D. candidate Yasmine Flynn-Arajdal studied iconographic representations of children in the Classic (ca. 250–950 AD) and Post-classic (ca. 950–1539 AD) imagery, as well as in ethnohistoric and ethnographic literature, to determine the importance of ear ornaments in Maya childhood and by what age they were received.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-ear-piercings-earliest-maya-rites.html</link>
                <category>Archaeology Social Sciences </category>
                <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 10:30:05 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684670854</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2021/maya.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Reddit field experiment examines what distinguishes lurkers from power users</title>
                <description>Online discussions are often dominated by a small group of active users, while the majority remain silent. This imbalance can distort perceptions of public opinion and fuel polarization.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-reddit-field-distinguishes-lurkers-power.html</link>
                <category>Social Sciences Political science </category>
                <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 16:44:15 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684607441</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/online-discussions-who.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>How emotions spread online following celebrity suicide news</title>
                <description>Reshare cascades on X (formerly Twitter) show how different expressed emotions unfold in the aftermath of celebrity suicides, according to a study published in PLOS One by Ehsan Nouri of the University of Virginia, U.S., and colleagues.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-emotions-online-celebrity-suicide-news.html</link>
                <category>Social Sciences </category>
                <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 14:00:03 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684577741</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/how-emotions-spread-on.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Personal risk tolerance has sweeping implications for how societies evolve</title>
                <description>In his biography of Elon Musk, historian Walter Isaacson describes a game of Texas Hold &quot;Em poker in which Musk went all in—on every hand.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-personal-tolerance-implications-societies-evolve.html</link>
                <category>Social Sciences Economics &amp; Business </category>
                <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 08:35:18 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684578102</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/personal-risk-toleranc.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Trust in science is low among minorities for a reason, research finds</title>
                <description>The COVID-19 pandemic prompted a nationwide conversation in the U.S. about how much people trust scientists and trained medical professionals. But for some communities, distrust has been the norm.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-science-minorities.html</link>
                <category>Social Sciences Political science </category>
                <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 09:20:04 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684494245</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2021/black-scientist.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Inequalities exist in even the most egalitarian societies, anthropologists find</title>
                <description>There is no such thing as a society where everyone is equal. That is the key message of new research that challenges the romantic ideal of a perfectly egalitarian human society.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-inequalities-egalitarian-societies-anthropologists.html</link>
                <category>Social Sciences Political science </category>
                <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 13:20:03 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684421655</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/egalitarianism.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Research reveals atypical Santas can succeed</title>
                <description>A naturally fluffy white beard, a round belly and a jolly laugh might seem like the keys to being a successful Santa Claus, but new research suggests that a calling to play the man with the bag full of toys is enough to help candidates overcome a lack of typical attributes for the role.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-reveals-atypical-santas-succeed.html</link>
                <category>Social Sciences Economics &amp; Business </category>
                <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 13:09:24 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684076086</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2024/santa-clause.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Pleasant-sounding words are easier to remember, pseudoword experiment shows</title>
                <description>Which words do we find beautiful? And do beautifully sounding words stick better in memory? A new study led by linguist Theresa Matzinger from the University of Vienna suggests that the phonemic composition of words influences how beautiful we perceive them to be, and how well we remember them. The findings are published in the journal PLOS One.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-pleasant-words-easier-pseudoword.html</link>
                <category>Social Sciences </category>
                <pubDate>Thu, 04 Dec 2025 11:11:45 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684068971</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/words.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Video-call glitches can have serious consequences</title>
                <description>A technical glitch during a Zoom call shouldn&#039;t be that big a deal, or lead someone to make a judgment about the person on the other end. But in actuality, glitches during face-to-face video calls—even when the glitch does not affect the transmission of information—can shatter the illusion of being across the table from the other person, evoking a creepy or eerie feeling known as &quot;uncanniness.&quot;</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-video-glitches-consequences.html</link>
                <category>Social Sciences Economics &amp; Business </category>
                <pubDate>Wed, 03 Dec 2025 12:51:20 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news683988661</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/video-call-glitches-ca.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Define your dating goals: Study shows clarity is key to dating satisfaction</title>
                <description>Single people who date without a clear understanding of what they are looking for in a relationship experience more loneliness and decreased life satisfaction, McGill researchers have found.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-dating-goals-clarity-key-satisfaction.html</link>
                <category>Social Sciences </category>
                <pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 12:49:16 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news683902125</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/online-dating.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Natural language found more complex than it strictly needs to be—and for good reason</title>
                <description>Human languages are complex phenomena. Around 7,000 languages are spoken worldwide, some with only a handful of remaining speakers, while others, such as Chinese, English, Spanish and Hindi, are spoken by billions. Despite their profound differences, they all share a common function: they convey information by combining individual words into phrases—groups of related words—which are then assembled into sentences. Each of these units has its own meaning, which in combination ultimately form a comprehensible whole.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-natural-language-complex-strictly-good.html</link>
                <category>Mathematics Social Sciences </category>
                <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 15:23:23 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news683824981</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/natural-language-is-mo.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Priming for planned sex increases desire, frequency in parents with young children</title>
                <description>Between the lack of sleep and free time, physical, hormonal and relationship changes, and juggling work and other life commitments, many couples find their sex lives take a hit in the transition to parenthood. Continuing through the early years of child rearing, this can have a negative impact on the overall relationship. While spontaneous sex is put on a pedestal in Western society, a new study led by researchers at York University&#039;s Faculty of Health found that encouraging couples with young children to plan sex led to increased desire and frequency.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-priming-sex-desire-frequency-parents.html</link>
                <category>Social Sciences </category>
                <pubDate>Mon, 01 Dec 2025 12:06:24 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news683813162</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2022/sex.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Six strategies identified to help households cut down on food waste</title>
                <description>Researchers from the Center for Food Policy at City St George&#039;s, University of London and Scotland&#039;s Rural College have set out six key areas for action that could help households cut down on food waste in a new comment article published in the journal Nature Human Behaviour.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-11-strategies-households-food.html</link>
                <category>Social Sciences </category>
                <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2025 10:20:02 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news683543939</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/food-waste-2.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>First &#039;Bible map&#039; published 500 years ago still influences how we think about borders, study suggests</title>
                <description>The first Bible to feature a map of the Holy Land was published 500 years ago in 1525. The map was initially printed the wrong way round—showing the Mediterranean to the East—but its inclusion set a precedent which continues to shape our understanding of state borders today, a new Cambridge study argues.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-11-bible-published-years-borders.html</link>
                <category>Social Sciences Political science </category>
                <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 19:10:01 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news683369041</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/first-bible-map-publis.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Social media research tool can lower political temperature—it could also lead to more user control over algorithms</title>
                <description>A new tool shows it is possible to turn down the partisan rancor in an X feed—without removing political posts and without the direct cooperation of the platform.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-11-social-media-tool-political-temperature.html</link>
                <category>Social Sciences Political science </category>
                <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 14:00:08 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news683309353</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2021/political-parties-1.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Instagram users overestimate their social media addiction, study suggests</title>
                <description>Instagram users may overestimate the extent to which they are addicted to the platform, according to research conducted on 1,204 U.S. adults published in Scientific Reports. The findings suggest that for most social media users, excessive use is driven by habit rather than genuine addiction.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-11-instagram-users-overestimate-social-media.html</link>
                <category>Social Sciences </category>
                <pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 11:00:04 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news683306521</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2022/instagram-1.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Mapping out the hidden mechanics behind why some fads spread like wildfire</title>
                <description>Whether it is a whole friendship group migrating to using iPhones or a swath of classmates wanting the latest Lululemon waterbottle, network scientists have uncovered the hidden mechanics behind social trends.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-11-hidden-mechanics-fads-wildfire.html</link>
                <category>Mathematics Social Sciences </category>
                <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 11:15:04 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news683291701</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/social-group.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>How personalized algorithms lead to a distorted view of reality</title>
                <description>The same personalized algorithms that deliver online content based on your previous choices on social media sites like YouTube also impair learning, a new study suggests.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-11-personalized-algorithms-distorted-view-reality.html</link>
                <category>Social Sciences </category>
                <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 09:16:03 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news683284561</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/person-using-phone.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>When gifts sting: Self-improvement presents may spark backlash and bad reviews</title>
                <description>New research from FIU Business shows that well-intended presents like weight-loss teas or gym memberships can unintentionally send the wrong message—and ultimately trigger negative online reviews that hurt brands.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-11-gifts-backlash-bad.html</link>
                <category>Social Sciences Economics &amp; Business </category>
                <pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 05:41:01 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news683012398</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2023/holiday-gift.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Rethinking where language comes from: Framework reveals complex interplay of biology and culture</title>
                <description>A new study challenges the idea that language stems from a single evolutionary root. Instead, it proposes that our ability to communicate evolved through the interaction of biology and culture, and involves multiple capacities, each with different evolutionary histories. The framework, published in Science, unites discoveries across disciplines to explain how the ability to learn to speak, develop grammar, and share meaning converged to create complex communication.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-11-rethinking-language-framework-reveals-complex.html</link>
                <category>Social Sciences </category>
                <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 16:41:04 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news682879262</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/rethinking-where-langu.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Humans bring gender bias to their interactions with AI, finds study</title>
                <description>Humans bring gender biases to their interactions with Artificial Intelligence (AI), according to new research from Trinity College Dublin and Ludwig-Maximilians Universität (LMU) Munich.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-11-humans-gender-bias-interactions-ai.html</link>
                <category>Social Sciences </category>
                <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 14:27:03 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news682871221</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/humans-bring-gender-bi.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>The Batman effect: The mere sight of the &#039;superhero&#039; can make us more altruistic</title>
                <description>If &quot;Batman&quot; appears on the scene, we immediately become more altruistic: in fact, research conducted by psychologists from the Università Cattolica del Sacro Cuore, Milan, shows that the sudden appearance of something unexpected—Batman—disrupts the predictability of everyday life and forces people to be present, breaking free from autopilot.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-11-batman-effect-mere-sight-superhero.html</link>
                <category>Social Sciences </category>
                <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 11:33:26 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news682860804</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/the-batman-effect-the.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Personality traits and zip code may determine political preferences</title>
                <description>Personality and zip code can help explain differences in political ideology, according to a new study from Northwestern University, which is the first to show the relationship between a person&#039;s personality traits and political preference varies, depending on where one lives.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-11-personality-traits-code-political.html</link>
                <category>Social Sciences Political science </category>
                <pubDate>Thu, 20 Nov 2025 09:38:03 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news682853881</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2022/politics.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Few women named as authors on retracted medical studies, analysis shows</title>
                <description>Women are underrepresented among authors of retracted publications, particularly in cases involving multiple retractions, according to a new study published in PLOS One by Paul Sebo of the University of Geneva, Switzerland.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-11-women-authors-retracted-medical-analysis.html</link>
                <category>Social Sciences Education </category>
                <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 14:00:03 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news682684201</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/medical-journal.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>People in isolated cities in Africa suffer more violence against civilians, study reveals</title>
                <description>Cities are often seen as hotspots of violence, with the assumption that larger cities are inherently more violent than smaller ones. This &quot;universal law&quot; of urban scaling has long shaped scientific thinking. But new research led by Complexity Science Hub (CSH) researcher Rafael Prieto-Curiel challenges this assumption. Published in Nature Communications, the study shows that it is not simply city size, but a city&#039;s level of isolation, that plays a crucial role in determining violence in Africa.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-11-people-isolated-cities-africa-violence.html</link>
                <category>Social Sciences Political science </category>
                <pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 05:00:03 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news682700281</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/people-in-isolated-cit.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Social media use soars as kids drop sports, reading and the arts</title>
                <description>In striking new statistics, experts warn of social media&#039;s growing grip on young people, with use among children and teens soaring by more than 200% since before COVID and showing no sign of decline.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-11-social-media-soars-kids-sports.html</link>
                <category>Social Sciences Education </category>
                <pubDate>Tue, 18 Nov 2025 20:30:02 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news682695059</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/teens-on-phones.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Enduring patterns in world&#039;s languages: One-third of grammatical &#039;universals&#039; stand up to rigorous testing</title>
                <description>Despite the vast diversity of human languages, specific grammatical patterns appear again and again. A new study reveals that around a third of the long-proposed &quot;linguistic universals&quot;—patterns thought to hold across all languages—are statistically supported when examined with state-of-the-art evolutionary methods.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-11-patterns-world-languages-grammatical-universals.html</link>
                <category>Social Sciences Education </category>
                <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 15:23:03 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news682615381</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/enduring-patterns-in-w.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Fake survey answers from AI could quietly sway election predictions</title>
                <description>Public opinion polls and other surveys rely on data to understand human behavior. New research from Dartmouth reveals that artificial intelligence can now corrupt public opinion surveys at scale—passing every quality check, mimicking real humans, and manipulating results without leaving a trace.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-11-fake-survey-ai-quietly-sway.html</link>
                <category>Social Sciences Political science </category>
                <pubDate>Mon, 17 Nov 2025 15:00:10 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news682602806</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/online.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                    </channel>
</rss>
