<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
<channel>
                    <title>Biology News - Evolution, Cell theory, Gene theory, Microbiology, Biotechnology</title>
            <link>https://phys.org/biology-news/</link>
            <language>en-us</language> 
            <description>Read the latest science news from Phys.org on biology, evolution, microbiology, biotechnology</description>
                        <item>
                <title>Italian bears living near villages have evolved to be smaller and less aggressive, finds study</title>
                <description>A paper in Molecular Biology and Evolution, reports that Italian bears living in areas with many villages evolved and became smaller and less aggressive.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-italian-villages-evolved-smaller-aggressive.html</link>
                <category>Evolution Ecology </category>
                <pubDate>Mon, 15 Dec 2025 00:10:01 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684756181</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/how-human-interaction.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>How a new algorithm predicts cell fate from just one genetic snapshot</title>
                <description>Researchers at Karolinska Institutet and KTH have developed a computational method that can reveal how cells change and specialize in the body. The study, which has been published in the journal PNAS, can provide important knowledge about why this process sometimes goes wrong and leads to disease.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-algorithm-reconstructs-cells-specialize-snapshots.html</link>
                <category>Cell &amp; Microbiology Molecular &amp; Computational biology </category>
                <pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2025 14:00:04 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684755570</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/new-algorithm-maps-how.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Scientists discover nine new species of butterfly from South America stored at London&#039;s Natural History Museum</title>
                <description>An international team of scientists have identified nine new species of butterflies using a combination of geographical, morphological and molecular analysis.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-scientists-species-butterfly-south-america.html</link>
                <category>Plants &amp; Animals Ecology </category>
                <pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2025 11:20:04 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684757056</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/scientists-discover-ni.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Biologists reveal ancient form of cell adhesion</title>
                <description>The cells of all animals—including humans—are characterized by their ability to adhere particularly well to surfaces in their environment. This mechanically stable adhesion enables the development of complex tissues and organs and is made possible by certain cell surface receptors called integrins. However, it is unclear how this form of cell adhesion developed over the course of evolution, as many single-celled organisms do not have integrin receptors.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-biologists-reveal-ancient-cell-adhesion.html</link>
                <category>Evolution Cell &amp; Microbiology </category>
                <pubDate>Sun, 14 Dec 2025 11:20:01 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684764421</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/biologists-reveal-anci.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Yuletide kissers, smooch without guilt: Research suggests your mistletoe didn&#039;t harm its tree host</title>
                <description>If mistletoe&#039;s status as a nutrient-stealing freeloader has been cooling your holiday ardor, new research led by an Oregon State University scientist may help relight the fire.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-yuletide-kissers-smooch-guilt-mistletoe.html</link>
                <category>Ecology </category>
                <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2025 12:10:10 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684850178</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/yuletide-kissers-smooc.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Misinformation is an inevitable biological reality across nature, researchers argue</title>
                <description>From claims that vaccines don&#039;t work to manipulated images and deliberately misrepresenting what politicians say, social media is often rife with misinformation. But far from being a recent phenomenon, there is nothing new about so-called &quot;fake news,&quot; according to a new paper published in the journal Interface. Researchers argue that misinformation is an inherent and inevitable property of biological systems, from bacteria to birds and human societies.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-misinformation-inevitable-biological-reality-nature.html</link>
                <category>Evolution Ecology </category>
                <pubDate>Sat, 13 Dec 2025 09:30:01 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684765243</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/misinformation-and-fak.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Unique bond identified as key to viral infection speed</title>
                <description>Viruses are typically described as tiny, perfectly geometric shells that pack genetic material with mathematical precision, but new research led by scientists at Penn State reveals a deliberate imbalance in their shape that helps them infect their hosts.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-unique-bond-key-viral-infection.html</link>
                <category>Cell &amp; Microbiology Molecular &amp; Computational biology </category>
                <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 14:00:02 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684666041</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/unique-bond-identified.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>A new medium for canine stem cells that doesn&#039;t contain any human components</title>
                <description>Canine induced pluripotent stem (iPS) cells possess the ability to differentiate into any type of cell, making them a useful tool for investigating common canine diseases and disease states, including those of humans.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-medium-canine-stem-cells-doesnt.html</link>
                <category>Cell &amp; Microbiology Biotechnology </category>
                <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 13:46:14 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684769562</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/pure-bred-new-stem-cel.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Smarter tools for peering into the microscopic world developed</title>
                <description>The microscopic organisms that fill our bodies, soils, oceans and atmosphere play essential roles in human health and the planet&#039;s ecosystems. Yet even with modern DNA sequencing, figuring out what these microbes are and how they are related to one another remains extremely difficult.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-smarter-tools-peering-microscopic-world.html</link>
                <category>Cell &amp; Microbiology Molecular &amp; Computational biology </category>
                <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 13:32:20 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684768721</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/smarter-tools-for-peer.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Glycitein biosynthetic pathway sheds light on soybean disease resistance</title>
                <description>Researchers from the Institute of Genetics and Developmental Biology of the Chinese Academy of Sciences (CAS) have uncovered the long-elusive biosynthetic pathway of glycitein, a key soybean isoflavonoid. They also reveal how its production determines the plant&#039;s resistance to Phytophthora sojae.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-glycitein-biosynthetic-pathway-soybean-disease.html</link>
                <category>Molecular &amp; Computational biology Agriculture </category>
                <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 11:49:20 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684762541</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/chinese-scientists-rev-3.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Genomic study reveals how vascular plants adapt to aquatic environments</title>
                <description>Aquatic plants are specialized evolutionary groups adapted to life in water. They play critical roles as food and medicinal supplies (e.g., lotus root and foxnut) and industrial raw materials (e.g., reeds), as well as in ecological restoration. While most aquatic lineages have independently evolved from terrestrial ancestors, the genomic dynamics underlying this adaptation remain largely unexplored.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-genomic-reveals-vascular-aquatic-environments.html</link>
                <category>Plants &amp; Animals Evolution </category>
                <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 11:37:23 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684761821</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/researchers-reveal-gen-2.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Roundworms discovered in Great Salt Lake are new to science</title>
                <description>Nematodes discovered in the Great Salt Lake belong to at least one species that is new to science, and possibly two. A University of Utah research team has published a new paper characterizing the tiny roundworm. The team gave it a name that honors the Indigenous tribe whose ancestral lands include the lake.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-roundworms-great-salt-lake-science.html</link>
                <category>Plants &amp; Animals Ecology </category>
                <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 09:20:06 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684753208</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/roundworms-discovered-2.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Storm study shows adaptive selection in southeast lizards</title>
                <description>How do intermittent events like hurricanes impact natural selection? How do animals adapt to challenging weather? A University of Rhode Island professor has set out to track natural selection in the Anolis lizard over time to see how the species has weathered hurricanes in the southeastern United States.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-storm-southeast-lizards.html</link>
                <category>Plants &amp; Animals Evolution </category>
                <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 09:08:16 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684752881</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/storm-study-shows-adap.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>&#039;Self-activation&#039; is part of the success strategy of parasitic weeds</title>
                <description>Parasitic weeds extract water and nutrients from their host plants. But what makes these parasites so successful? A study led by Prof Susann Wicke from the Institute for Evolution and Biodiversity at the University of Münster and published in  Science Advances has shown that certain parasitic plants activate their feeding organs (haustoria) independently of the host plant. This strategy increases their ability to successfully infest the host.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-success-strategy-parasitic-weeds.html</link>
                <category>Plants &amp; Animals Ecology </category>
                <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 08:42:10 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684751321</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/self-activation-is-par.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Swedish freshwater bacteria reveal lost genes and unexpected photosynthesis abilities</title>
                <description>Bacteria are among the most diverse and ancient forms of life on Earth. Yet, much of what is known about them comes from a small group of species, mostly studied for their roles in human health.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-swedish-freshwater-bacteria-reveal-lost.html</link>
                <category>Evolution Cell &amp; Microbiology </category>
                <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 05:00:08 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684675061</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/swedish-freshwater-bac-1.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Plant hormone allows lifelong control of proteins in living animal for first time</title>
                <description>Researchers have found a way to control protein levels inside different tissues of a whole, living animal for the first time. The method lets scientists dial protein levels up or down with great precision during the animal&#039;s entire life, a technological advance which can help them study the molecular underpinnings of aging and disease.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-hormone-lifelong-proteins-animal.html</link>
                <category>Biotechnology Molecular &amp; Computational biology </category>
                <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 05:00:03 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684681616</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/plant-hormone-allows-l.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Polar bears may be adapting to survive warmer climates, says study</title>
                <description>New research reveals a link between rising temperatures and changes in polar bear DNA, which may be helping them adapt and survive in increasingly challenging environments.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-polar-survive-warmer-climates.html</link>
                <category>Plants &amp; Animals Evolution </category>
                <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 20:00:06 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684664381</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2023/polar-bear.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Tracing a path through photosynthesis to food security</title>
                <description>The energy that plants capture from sunlight through photosynthesis provides the source of nearly all of humanity&#039;s food. Yet the process of photosynthesis has inefficiencies that limit crop productivity, especially in a rapidly changing world. A new review by University of Illinois scientists and collaborators reflects on how improving photosynthesis can bring us closer to food security.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-path-photosynthesis-food.html</link>
                <category>Molecular &amp; Computational biology Agriculture </category>
                <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 16:58:28 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684694681</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/tracing-a-path-through-1.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Fungal allies arm plant roots against disease by rewriting the rules of infection</title>
                <description>Scientists have discovered that beneficial root-dwelling fungi boost plant resilience to disease by remodeling the plant cell membrane at pathogen infection sites—offering critical new insights into how plants coordinate defenses in complex natural environments.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-fungal-allies-arm-roots-disease.html</link>
                <category>Plants &amp; Animals Cell &amp; Microbiology </category>
                <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 16:00:01 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684690647</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/fungal-allies-arm-plan-2.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>How extreme weather events affect agricultural trade between US states</title>
                <description>The U.S. is largely self-sufficient in agricultural food production, supported by a well-developed storage and interstate trade system. However, extreme weather events put increasing pressure on agriculture, potentially impacting the country&#039;s ability to provide food for its growing population and underscoring the importance of maintaining a resilient food supply chain.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-extreme-weather-events-affect-agricultural.html</link>
                <category>Agriculture </category>
                <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 15:50:50 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684690631</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/how-extreme-weather-ev.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Chinese intertidal shellfish farming: An unexpected fuel station for millions of migrating shorebirds</title>
                <description>China&#039;s tidal flats feed people and mollusk-eating migrating shorebirds such as red knots, great knots and Eurasian oystercatchers. Under good management, these flats used for aquaculture markedly reduce human disturbance on tidal wetlands.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-chinese-intertidal-shellfish-farming-unexpected.html</link>
                <category>Plants &amp; Animals Ecology </category>
                <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 15:03:24 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684687781</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/chinese-intertidal-she.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Lab-developed mosquitoes prevent malaria parasite development, paving way for future field trials</title>
                <description>In a new study published in Nature, scientists have successfully developed genetically modified mosquitoes in Tanzania that block the transmission of malaria. The team includes researchers from the Ifakara Health Institute (IHI) and the National Institute for Medical Research (NIMR) in Tanzania, in partnership with the Swiss Tropical and Public Health Institute (Swiss TPH) and the Imperial College London as part of the Transmission Zero program.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-lab-mosquitoes-malaria-parasite-paving.html</link>
                <category>Biotechnology Molecular &amp; Computational biology </category>
                <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 14:20:40 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684685201</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/lab-developed-mosquito.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Warblers borrow color-related genes from evolutionary neighbors, study finds</title>
                <description>Wood warblers, also called New World warblers, are some of the most colorful birds in North America, with more than a hundred species in the family ranging in color from yellow, orange and red to blue, green and pink. A new study led by researchers at Penn State has uncovered several instances of the birds passing color-related genes to other species of wood warblers, including those that are not closely related.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-warblers-genes-evolutionary-neighbors.html</link>
                <category>Evolution Ecology </category>
                <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 14:00:04 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684608581</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/warblers-borrow-color.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Shape-shifting cell channel reveals new target for precision drugs</title>
                <description>From small ions to large molecules, cellular gates control what can pass in and out of cells. But how one such gate, called pannexin-1 (PANX1), can handle vastly different cargo sizes has remained a long-standing mystery.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-shifting-cell-channel-reveals-precision.html</link>
                <category>Cell &amp; Microbiology Molecular &amp; Computational biology </category>
                <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 12:50:15 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684679801</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/shape-shifting-cell-ch.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Scientists teach helices to switch shapes</title>
                <description>Researchers at the University of Jyväskylä have discovered a simple way to program synthetic molecules so they can form specific spiral-like structures by embedding instructions directly into their sequence. This breakthrough could lead to new smart materials and molecular devices that adapt to their surroundings.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-scientists-helices.html</link>
                <category>Biotechnology Molecular &amp; Computational biology </category>
                <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 11:30:04 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684672906</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/scientists-teach-helic.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Orca tail dolphins to hunt salmon—and may share the catch</title>
                <description>Killer whales or orca (Orcinus orca) have been observed hunting with Pacific white-sided dolphins (Lagenorhynchus obliquidens) in the waters off British Columbia, Canada, and sharing fish scraps with them after making a kill, according to research published in Scientific Reports.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-orca-tail-dolphins-salmon.html</link>
                <category>Plants &amp; Animals Ecology </category>
                <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 11:00:09 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684578221</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/marine-ecology-killer.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>How to build a genome: Scientists release troubleshooting manual for synthetic life</title>
                <description>Leading synthetic biologists have shared hard-won lessons from their decade-long quest to build the world&#039;s first synthetic eukaryotic genome in a Nature Biotechnology paper. Their insights could accelerate development of the next generation of engineered organisms, from climate-resilient crops to custom-built cell factories.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-genome-scientists-manual-synthetic-life.html</link>
                <category>Biotechnology Molecular &amp; Computational biology </category>
                <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 11:00:04 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684578521</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/how-to-build-a-genome.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>A new species of tiny orange frog discovered in Brazil&#039;s cloud forests</title>
                <description>Despite the vast numbers of animal species already identified, the natural world is still capable of springing a few surprises. Deep in the cloud forests of the Serra do Quiriri mountain range in the southern Brazilian Atlantic Forest, an international team of scientists has discovered an entirely new species of tiny frog, named Brachycephalus lulai.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-species-tiny-orange-frog-brazil.html</link>
                <category>Plants &amp; Animals Ecology </category>
                <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 10:30:03 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684670825</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/a-new-species-of-tiny-2.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Spillover from protected areas can help ecosystems survive</title>
                <description>Spillovers from protected areas such as national parks and wildlife reserves can play a significant role in boosting biodiversity beyond their boundaries with potential benefits to people through ecosystem services such as climate mitigation, water retention and erosion control.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-spillover-areas-ecosystems-survive.html</link>
                <category>Ecology </category>
                <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 10:04:11 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684669842</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/spillover-from-protect.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Migratory birds&#039; stunning precision in flight revealed by new data loggers</title>
                <description>Red-backed shrikes fly thousands of kilometers to reach Africa—and they do so with astonishing precision. Aided by new technology, researchers at Lund University in Sweden have been able to track the birds&#039; journeys in detail. It turns out that they may have a more complex genetic migration program than researchers have previously been able to show. The study is published in Proceedings of the Royal Society B: Biological Sciences.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-migratory-birds-stunning-precision-flight.html</link>
                <category>Plants &amp; Animals Ecology </category>
                <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 10:03:22 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684669781</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/new-technology-reveals-3.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                    </channel>
</rss>
