<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
<channel>
                    <title>Earth News - Earth Science News, Earth Science, Climate Change</title>
            <link>https://phys.org/earth-news/</link>
            <language>en-us</language> 
            <description>Earth science research, climate change, and global warming.  The latest news and updates from Phys.org</description>
                        <item>
                <title>Feedback loops from oil fields accelerate Arctic warming and other atmospheric changes, study shows</title>
                <description>The climate is changing and nowhere is it changing faster than at Earth&#039;s poles. Researchers at Penn State have painted a comprehensive picture of the chemical processes taking place in the Arctic and found that there are multiple, separate interactions impacting the atmosphere.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-feedback-loops-oil-fields-arctic.html</link>
                <category>Earth Sciences Environment </category>
                <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 12:16:21 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684764161</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/feedback-loops-acceler.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Earthquake rupture along Main Marmara Fault shows eastward progression towards Istanbul</title>
                <description>In April 2025, the Main Marmara Fault below the Sea of Marmara in northwestern Türkiye experienced its largest earthquake in over 60 years. In a study published in Science, a team of researchers led by Prof. Dr. Patricia Martínez-Garzón from the GFZ Helmholtz Center for Geosciences in Potsdam, Germany, analyzes nearly two decades of seismic data framing the 2025 April magnitude M 6.2 earthquake.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-earthquake-rupture-main-marmara-fault.html</link>
                <category>Earth Sciences </category>
                <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 11:58:41 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684763081</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/eastward-earthquake-ru.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>&#039;Hidden&#039; contrails in cirrus clouds contribute to climate warming, research finds</title>
                <description>Researchers at the Institute for Meteorology at Leipzig University have, for the first time, determined the climatic impact of contrails that form within natural cirrus clouds. Contrails account for the largest share of aviation&#039;s climate impact beyond carbon dioxide emissions.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-hidden-contrails-cirrus-clouds-contribute.html</link>
                <category>Earth Sciences Environment </category>
                <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 09:20:23 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684753601</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/hidden-contrails-in-ci.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Global measures consistently underestimate food insecurity: 1 in 5 who suffer from hunger may go uncounted</title>
                <description>International humanitarian aid organizations rely on analyses from the Integrated Food Security Phase Classification (IPC) system, a global partnership that monitors and classifies the severity of food insecurity to help target assistance where and when it is most needed.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-global-underestimate-food-insecurity-hunger.html</link>
                <category>Environment </category>
                <pubDate>Fri, 12 Dec 2025 05:00:05 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684681605</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/global-measures-consis.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Hidden fuel for ocean microbes: Urea emerges as key energy source for marine ammonia oxidizers</title>
                <description>Ammonia-oxidizing archaea (AOA) are some of the most abundant microorganisms in the ocean and play a key role in nitrogen cycling. Yet, despite their ubiquity, scientists have long puzzled over how these microbes can flourish in the nutrient-poor waters of the open ocean, where their main nitrogen and energy source, ammonium, is often vanishingly scarce.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-hidden-fuel-ocean-microbes-urea.html</link>
                <category>Earth Sciences Environment </category>
                <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 12:49:18 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684679741</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/the-hidden-fuel-for-oc-2.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Widespread sediments beneath Greenland make its ice more vulnerable to warming</title>
                <description>In an age of rising sea levels, as polar ice sheets melt in a climate warmed by fossil fuel emissions, climate modelers are racing to understand what the future might hold for coastlines around the world. But uncertainties about how fast polar ice might melt make predicting coastal inundation difficult. Now, scientists think they&#039;ve helped make one of those uncertainties, the material conditions underneath the Greenland ice sheet, smaller.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-widespread-sediments-beneath-greenland-ice.html</link>
                <category>Earth Sciences Environment </category>
                <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 12:22:25 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684678121</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/widespread-sediments-b.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Wintertime spike in oceanic iron levels detected near Hawaii</title>
                <description>Around the world, phytoplankton in the upper ocean help to cycle key nutrients and regulate Earth&#039;s climate by absorbing carbon dioxide. These photosynthesizing organisms rely on dissolved iron as an essential micronutrient, meaning that when iron levels drop, phytoplankton activity drops, too.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-wintertime-spike-oceanic-iron-hawaii.html</link>
                <category>Earth Sciences Environment </category>
                <pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 12:20:12 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684678001</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/wintertime-spike-in-oc.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Spending less can deliver more climate-friendly nutrition</title>
                <description>Eating healthily can save money and also cause less greenhouse gas emissions than most people&#039;s current food choices, according to a new global study that examined food costs, nutrition, and climate impact around the world.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-climate-friendly-nutrition.html</link>
                <category>Environment </category>
                <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 15:52:31 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684604321</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/spending-less-can-deli.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>A new framework addresses fair distribution of emissions</title>
                <description>Ten years ago, on 12 December 2015, the Paris Climate Agreement was signed at the UN Climate Conference. In order to limit global warming to well below two degrees, only a certain amount of CO2 may be emitted worldwide. While the focus was originally on national emission targets, more than 200 subnational regions and almost 300 cities have now adopted their own targets.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-framework-fair-emissions.html</link>
                <category>Environment </category>
                <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 14:43:18 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684600181</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/fair-distribution-of-e.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Wildfire smoke lofted into atmosphere could affect Earth&#039;s climate</title>
                <description>Some wildfires are so intense, they create their own weather—thunderstorms driven by heat that hurtle smoke as high as 10 miles into the sky like giant chimneys.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-wildfire-lofted-atmosphere-affect-earth.html</link>
                <category>Earth Sciences Environment </category>
                <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 14:00:14 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684501061</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/sky-high-smoke.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Iberian peninsula is rotating clockwise, according to new geodynamic data</title>
                <description>Asier Madarieta, a researcher in the EHU&#039;s HGI (Water Environmental Processes) group, has analyzed how the Earth&#039;s crust is being compressed and deformed in the field where Eurasia and Africa meet in the Western Mediterranean. His work contributes towards understanding this complex contact field better as well as opening the door to identifying the faults and structures that could lead to earthquakes or deformations on the peninsula.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-iberian-peninsula-rotating-clockwise-geodynamic.html</link>
                <category>Earth Sciences </category>
                <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 13:08:57 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684594421</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/iberian-peninsula-is-r.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Tropical cyclones and the carbon cycle: New insights from a model simulation</title>
                <description>For the first time, scientists have resolved extremely intense tropical cyclones and their effect on the ocean carbon cycle in a global Earth system model. Using two category-4 hurricanes in the North Atlantic as examples, the study reveals a cascade of physical-biogeochemical effects including uptake of carbon dioxide and regional-scale phytoplankton bloom. The results are published in the Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-tropical-cyclones-carbon-insights-simulation.html</link>
                <category>Earth Sciences Environment </category>
                <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 12:22:35 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684591721</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/tropical-cyclones-and.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>A new &#039;hypertropical&#039; climate is emerging in the Amazon, exposing trees to deadly stress</title>
                <description>The Amazon rainforest is slowly transitioning to a new, hotter climate with more frequent and intense droughts—conditions that haven&#039;t been seen on Earth for tens of millions of years.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-hypertropical-climate-emerging-amazon-exposing.html</link>
                <category>Earth Sciences Environment </category>
                <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 11:00:25 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684583506</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/a-new-hypertropical-cl.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Study suggests Earth&#039;s inner core may have onion-like layered structure</title>
                <description>An international research team may have found an explanation for seismic anomalies, the noticeable deviations in the behavior of earthquake waves, in Earth&#039;s inner core.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-earth-core-onion-layered.html</link>
                <category>Earth Sciences </category>
                <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 10:50:01 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684585219</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/study-suggests-earths.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Satellite tracking helps map massive rupture of 2025 Myanmar earthquake</title>
                <description>The March 28, 2025, Myanmar earthquake is giving scientists a rare look into how some of the world&#039;s most dangerous fault systems behave, including California&#039;s San Andreas Fault. Earthquakes are notoriously messy and complex, but this one struck along an unusually straight and geologically &quot;mature&quot; fault, creating near-ideal conditions for researchers to observe how Earth releases energy during a major continental rupture.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-satellite-tracking-massive-rupture-myanmar.html</link>
                <category>Earth Sciences </category>
                <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 10:24:16 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684584572</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/satellite-data-helps-u.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Global warming amplifies extreme day-to-day temperature swings, study shows</title>
                <description>A new study has revealed that rapid, large-scale day-to-day temperature fluctuations have intensified amid global warming, representing a distinct climate hazard with impacts on human health. This growing volatility creates a weather pattern akin to a &quot;climate roller coaster,&quot; exposing populations to more frequent and sharp shifts between temperature extremes.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-global-amplifies-extreme-day-temperature.html</link>
                <category>Environment </category>
                <pubDate>Wed, 10 Dec 2025 10:23:06 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684584547</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/new-study-reveals-glob-1.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Ocean current and seabed shape influence warm water circulation under ice shelves, research reveals</title>
                <description>New research reveals how the speed of ocean currents and the shape of the seabed influence the amount of heat flowing underneath Antarctic ice shelves, contributing to melting.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-ocean-current-seabed-circulation-ice.html</link>
                <category>Earth Sciences Environment </category>
                <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 19:10:05 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684507602</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/ocean-current-and-seab.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Geomorphological approach evaluates Galápagos watersheds</title>
                <description>Galápagos is a living laboratory where every environmental decision matters. On Santa Cruz, the most populated island of the archipelago, freshwater is a limited and increasingly vulnerable resource due to urban growth, agricultural pressure, saltwater intrusion, and climate change. In this context, understanding how water behaves across the landscape becomes essential for water security.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-geomorphological-approach-galpagos-watersheds.html</link>
                <category>Earth Sciences Environment </category>
                <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 16:34:10 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684520441</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/water-for-all-a-study.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Antarctica&#039;s only native insect is already eating microplastics</title>
                <description>A global research team led by researchers from the University of Kentucky Martin-Gatton College of Agriculture, Food and Environment has found that Antarctica&#039;s only native insect is already ingesting microplastics, even in one of the planet&#039;s most remote regions.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-antarctica-native-insect-microplastics.html</link>
                <category>Environment </category>
                <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 15:30:01 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684516405</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/antarcticas-toughest-i.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Fast-tracking a natural climate solution by compressing millennia of carbon capture into hours</title>
                <description>What if it were possible to take a very slow geological process, one that takes thousands of years in nature, and speed it up so that it happens within hours, in order to slow the rate of global warming?</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-fast-tracking-natural-climate-solution.html</link>
                <category>Earth Sciences Environment </category>
                <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 15:20:01 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684515490</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/fast-tracking-a-natura.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Chaotic 3D currents form multiple microplastic &#039;attractors&#039; beneath the ocean surface, study finds</title>
                <description>The ocean is saturated with microplastics. While we know the location of the great garbage patches, where plastic particles may accumulate below the ocean surface remains unknown. The vastness of the ocean means particle sampling data are sparse, but modeling how particles aggregate in 3D fluid flows can help determine where to look.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-chaotic-3d-currents-multiple-microplastic.html</link>
                <category>Earth Sciences Environment </category>
                <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 11:00:01 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684414661</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/modeling-microplastic.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>2025 on track to tie second hottest year on record: EU monitor</title>
                <description>The planet is on track to log its second hottest year on record in 2025, tied with 2023 after a historic high in 2024, Europe&#039;s global warming monitor said Tuesday.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-track-hottest-year-eu.html</link>
                <category>Environment </category>
                <pubDate>Tue, 09 Dec 2025 04:24:07 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684476611</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/the-planet-is-on-track.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>NYC congestion pricing cuts air pollution by 22% in Manhattan, study finds</title>
                <description>Since New York City introduced congestion pricing in January 2025, the state has heralded significant reductions in traffic and rush hour delays, fewer crashes and noise complaints, and toll revenue projected to hit $500 million by the end of the year.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-nyc-congestion-pricing-air-pollution.html</link>
                <category>Environment </category>
                <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 11:55:35 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684417301</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/congestion-pricing-imp.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Greenhouse gases projected to sharply increase extreme flooding in Central Himalayas</title>
                <description>Rising greenhouse gas emissions could see the size of extreme floods in the Central Himalayas increase by between as much as 73% and 84% by the end of this century.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-greenhouse-gases-sharply-extreme-central.html</link>
                <category>Earth Sciences Environment </category>
                <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 11:10:06 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684412290</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/greenhouse-gases-to-in.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Temporary carbon removals can offset methane&#039;s short-term warming impact</title>
                <description>Carbon removal projects could prove vital in offsetting methane emissions—the second largest contributor to global warming.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-temporary-carbon-offset-methane-short.html</link>
                <category>Environment </category>
                <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 10:40:08 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684412206</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/temporary-carbon-remov.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>When companies &#039;go green,&#039; air quality impacts can vary dramatically</title>
                <description>Many organizations are taking actions to shrink their carbon footprint, such as purchasing electricity from renewable sources or reducing air travel. Both actions would cut greenhouse gas emissions, but which offers greater societal benefits?</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-companies-green-air-quality-impacts.html</link>
                <category>Environment </category>
                <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 10:37:39 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684412562</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/when-companies-go-gree.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Adrift like Shackleton: Robot float survives Antarctic ice</title>
                <description>A robotic float has measured the temperature and salinity from parts of the ocean never sampled before—underneath massive floating ice shelves in East Antarctica.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-adrift-shackleton-robot-survives-antarctic.html</link>
                <category>Earth Sciences Environment </category>
                <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 08:51:13 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684406206</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/adrift-like-shackleton-1.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>When climate risk hits home, people listen: Local details can enhance disaster preparedness messaging</title>
                <description>A subtle change in how climate risk is communicated—mentioning a person&#039;s local area—can significantly increase attention to disaster preparedness messages, according to a new study by researchers at the Stockholm School of Economics and Harvard University, published in Nature Human Behaviour. The findings offer a practical, low-cost strategy for governments, insurers and local authorities seeking to boost climate resilience in vulnerable communities.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-climate-home-people-local-disaster.html</link>
                <category>Environment </category>
                <pubDate>Mon, 08 Dec 2025 05:00:01 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684083405</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/hurricane-route.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>Storms in the Southern Ocean are producing more rain—and the consequences could be global</title>
                <description>If you ever find yourself on Macquarie Island—a narrow, wind-lashed ridge halfway between Tasmania and Antarctica—the first thing you&#039;ll notice is the wildlife. Elephant seals sprawl across dark beaches. King penguins march up mossy slopes. Albatrosses circle over vast, treeless uplands.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-storms-southern-ocean-consequences-global.html</link>
                <category>Earth Sciences Environment </category>
                <pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 12:00:01 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684150861</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/storms-in-the-southern.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                        <item>
                <title>New approach narrows uncertainty in future warming and remaining carbon budget for 2°C</title>
                <description>How much the planet warms with each ton of carbon dioxide remains one of the most important questions in climate science, but there is uncertainty in predicting it. This uncertainty hinders governments, businesses and communities from setting clear emission-reduction targets and preparing for the impacts of climate change.</description>
                <link>https://phys.org/news/2025-12-approach-narrows-uncertainty-future-carbon.html</link>
                <category>Earth Sciences Environment </category>
                <pubDate>Sat, 06 Dec 2025 10:00:01 EST</pubDate>
                <guid isPermaLink="false">news684166598</guid>
                <media:thumbnail url="https://scx1.b-cdn.net/csz/news/tmb/2025/new-approach-narrows-u-1.jpg" width="90" height="90" />            </item>
                    </channel>
</rss>
